<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>design on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/categories/design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in design on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/categories/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Type-2 and Type-5 EPVN on vQFX 10k in UnetLab</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/10/26/qfx-unl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/10/26/qfx-unl/</guid>
      <description>News about UnetLab Those who read my blog regularly know that I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of a network simulator called UnetLab. For the last two years I&amp;rsquo;ve done all my labbing in UNL and was constantly surprised by how extensible and stable it has been. I believe that projects like this are very important to our networking community because they help train the new generation of network engineers and enable them to expand their horizons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iBGP Fall-over Trick</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2015/06/11/ibgp-fallover-trick/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2015/06/11/ibgp-fallover-trick/</guid>
      <description>BGP fall-over is a neat BGP convergence optimisation technique whereby BGP peering is brought down as soon as the route to neighbor disappears from a routing table. The difference between external and internal BGP is that the former usually peers over a directly-attached interface so that when the interface to neighbor is disconnected, route is withdrawn from the routing table which triggers eBGP fall-over to bring down the neighborship. iBGP, on the other hand, normally uses device loopbacks to establish peering sessions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best practices for enterprise IP routing</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2015/06/03/ent-ip-routing-bcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2015/06/03/ent-ip-routing-bcp/</guid>
      <description>What motivated me to write this post is a state of the IP routing of some of the enterprise networks I&amp;rsquo;ve seen. A quick show ip route command reveals a non-disentanglable mixture of dynamic and static route with multiple points of redistribution and complex, rigid filtering rules, something you&amp;rsquo;d only see in your bad dream or a CCIE-level lab. It certainly takes a good engineer to understand how it works and even that can take up to several hours.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>