<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EVPN on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/tags/evpn/</link>
    <description>Recent content in EVPN on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/tags/evpn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack SDN - OpenContrail With BGP VPN</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2018/01/02/os-contrail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2018/01/02/os-contrail/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on the trend started in my previous post about OpenDaylight, I&amp;rsquo;ll move on to the next open-source product that uses BGP VPNs for optimal North-South traffic forwarding. OpenContrail is one of the most popular SDN solutions for OpenStack. It was one of the first hybrid SDN solutions, offering both pure overlay and overlay/underlay integration. It is the default SDN platform of choice for Mirantis Cloud Platform, it has multiple large-scale deployments in companies like Workday and AT&amp;amp;T.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenStack SDN - OpenDaylight With BGP VPN</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/12/15/os-odl-netvirt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/12/15/os-odl-netvirt/</guid>
      <description>For the last 5 years OpenStack has been the training ground for a lot of emerging DC SDN solutions. OpenStack integration use case was one of the most compelling and easiest to implement thanks to the limited and suboptimal implementation of the native networking stack. Today, in 2017, features like L2 population, local ARP responder, L2 gateway integration, distributed routing and service function chaining have all become available in vanilla OpenStack and don&amp;rsquo;t require a proprietary SDN controller anymore.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type-2 and Type-5 EPVN on vQFX 10k in UnetLab</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/10/26/qfx-unl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/10/26/qfx-unl/</guid>
      <description>News about UnetLab Those who read my blog regularly know that I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of a network simulator called UnetLab. For the last two years I&amp;rsquo;ve done all my labbing in UNL and was constantly surprised by how extensible and stable it has been. I believe that projects like this are very important to our networking community because they help train the new generation of network engineers and enable them to expand their horizons.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>