<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cue on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/tags/cue/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cue on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/tags/cue/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Automation with CUE - Working with YANG-based APIs</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-12-cue-yang/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-12-cue-yang/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I mentioned that CUE can help you work with both &amp;ldquo;industry-standard&amp;rdquo; semi-structured APIs and fully structured APIs where data is modelled using OpenAPI or JSON schema. However, there was an elephant in the room that I conveniently ignored but without which no conversation about network automation would be complete. With this post, I plan to rectify my previous omission and explain how you can use CUE to work with YANG-based APIs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Automation with CUE - Advanced workflows</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-11-cue-networking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-11-cue-networking/</guid>
      <description>What I&amp;rsquo;ve covered in the previous blog post about CUE and Ansible were isolated use cases, disconnected islands in the sea of network automation. The idea behind that was to simplify the introduction of CUE into existing network automation workflows. However, this does not mean CUE is limited to those use cases and, in fact, CUE is most powerful when it&amp;rsquo;s used end-to-end &amp;mdash; both to generate device configurations and to orchestrate interactions with external systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Automation with CUE - Augmenting Ansible workflows</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-11-cue-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-11-cue-ansible/</guid>
      <description>Hardly any conversation about network automation that happens these days can avoid the topic of automation frameworks. Amongst the few that are still actively developed, Ansible is by far the most popular choice. Ansible ecosystem has been growing rapidly over the last few years, with modules being contributed by both internal (Redhat) and external (community) developers. Having the backing of one of the largest open-source first companies has allowed Ansible to spread into all areas of infrastructure &amp;ndash; from server automation to cloud provisioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Automation with CUE - Introduction</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-10-cue-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2022-10-cue-intro/</guid>
      <description>In the past few years, network automation has made its way from a new and fancy way of configuring devices to a well-recognized industry practice. What started as a series of &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; examples has evolved into an entire discipline with books, professional certifications and dedicated career paths. It&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that today, most large-scale networks (&amp;gt;100 devices) are at least deployed (day 0) and sometimes managed (day 1+) using an automated workflow.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>