<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chef on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/tags/chef/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chef on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/tags/chef/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Automating the Build of OpenStack Lab (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/09/09/os-lab-p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/09/09/os-lab-p2/</guid>
      <description>In the last post we&amp;rsquo;ve seen how to use Chef to automate the build of a 3-node OpenStack cloud. The only thing remaining is to build an underlay network supporting communication between the nodes, which is what we&amp;rsquo;re going to do next. The build process will, again, be relatively simple and will include only a few manual steps, but before we get there let me go over some of the decisions and assumptions I&amp;rsquo;ve made in my network design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automating the Build of OpenStack Lab (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/08/26/os-lab-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2016/08/26/os-lab-p1/</guid>
      <description>Now that I&amp;rsquo;m finally beginning to settle down at my new place of residence I can start spending more time on research and blogging. I have left off right before I was about to start exploring the native OpenStack distributed virtual routing function. However as I&amp;rsquo;d started rebuilding my OpenStack lab from scratch I realised that I was doing a lot of repetitive tasks which can be easily automated. Couple that with the fact that I needed to learn Chef for my new work and you&amp;rsquo;ve got this blogpost describing a few Chef cookbooks (similar to Ansible&amp;rsquo;s playbook) automating all those manual steps described in my earlier blogposts 1 and 2.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>