<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>YANG on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/tags/yang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in YANG on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/tags/yang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using YANG Models in Ansible to Configure and Verify State of IOS-XE and JUNOS Devices</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/04/04/ansible-yang/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/04/04/ansible-yang/</guid>
      <description>The idea of using Ansible for configuration changes and state verification is not new. However the approach I&amp;rsquo;m going to demonstrate in this post, using YANG and NETCONF, will have a few notable differences:
 I will not use any templates and absolutely no XML/JSON for device config generation All changes will be pushed through a single, vendor and model-independent Ansible module State verification will be done with no pattern-matching or screen-scraping All configuration and operational state will be based on a couple of YAML files To demonstrate the model-agnostic behaviour I will use a mixture of vendor&amp;rsquo;s native, IETF and OpenConfig YANG models  I hope this promise is exciting enough so without further ado, let&amp;rsquo;s get cracking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Cisco IOS XE With YANG-based YAML Files</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/03/13/yaml-yang/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/03/13/yaml-yang/</guid>
      <description>XML, just like many more structured data formats, was not designed to be human-friendly. That&amp;rsquo;s why many network engineers lose interest in YANG as soon as the conversation gets to the XML part. JSON is a much more human-readable alternative, however very few devices support RESTCONF, and the ones that do may have buggy implementations. At the same time, a lot of network engineers have happily embraced Ansible, which extensively uses YAML.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Cisco IOS XE With YDK and OpenDaylight</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/02/22/odl-ydk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/02/22/odl-ydk/</guid>
      <description>In the previous posts about NETCONF and RESTCONF I&amp;rsquo;ve demonstrated how to interact with Cisco IOS XE device directly from the Linux shell of my development VM. This approach works fine in some cases, e.g. whenever I setup a new DC fabric, I would make calls directly to the devices I&amp;rsquo;m configuring. However, it becomes impractical in the Ops world where change is constant and involves a large number of devices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to YANG Programming and RESTCONF on Cisco IOS XE</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/02/15/restconf-yang/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/02/15/restconf-yang/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post I have demonstrated how to make changes to interface configuration of Cisco IOS XE device using the standard IETF model. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll show how to use Cisco&amp;rsquo;s native YANG model to modify static IP routes. To make things even more interesting I&amp;rsquo;ll use RESTCONF, an HTTP-based sibling of NETCONF.
RESTCONF primer RESTCONF is a very close functional equivalent of NETCONF. Instead of SSH, RESTCONF relies on HTTP to interact with configuration data and operational state of the network device and encodes all exchanged data in either XML or JSON.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started With NETCONF and YANG on Cisco IOS XE</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/01/25/netconf-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/blog/2017/01/25/netconf-intro/</guid>
      <description>To kick things off I will show how to use ncclient and pyang to configure interfaces on Cisco IOS XE device. In order to make sure everyone is on the same page and to provide some reference points for the remaining parts of the post, I would first need to cover some basic theory about NETCONF, XML and YANG.
NETCONF primer NETCONF is a network management protocol that runs over a secure transport (SSH, TLS etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>