<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Devops | Network-oriented programming]]></title>
  <link href="http://networkop.github.io/blog/categories/devops/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://networkop.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-24T23:11:35-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://networkop.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Kashin]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mmkashin@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Network-CI Part 1 - Automatically Building a VM With UNetLab and Jenkins]]></title>
    <link href="http://networkop.github.io/blog/2016/02/25/network-ci-dev-setup/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://networkop.github.io/blog/2016/02/25/network-ci-dev-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Traditionally, the first post in the series describes how to setup a development environment. This time I&rsquo;ll do it DevOps-style. I&rsquo;ll show how to use Packer to automatically create and configure a VM with UNetLab and Jenkins pre-installed.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/packer-unl-jenkins.png" title="Packer-UNL-Jenkins" ></p>

<h2>Packer intro</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.packer.io/">Packer</a> is a tool that can automatically create virtual machines for different hypervisors and cloud platforms. The goal is to produce identically configured VMs for either VirtualBox, VMWare, Amazon or Google clouds based on a single template file. If you&rsquo;re familiar with <a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/docs/">Vagrant</a>, then you can also use Packer to create custom Vagrant boxes. In our case, however, we&rsquo;re only concerned about VMWare since it&rsquo;s the only <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypervisor">type-2 hypervisor</a> that supports nested hardware virtualisation (e.g. Intel VT-x), a feature required by UNetLab to run some of the emulated images.</p>

<p>Packer builds VMs using a special template file. At the very least, this file describes how to:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Build a VM</p></li>
<li><p>Provision and configure apps on a VM</p></li>
</ul>


<p>These two actions correspond to the <code>builders</code> and <code>provisioners</code> sections of the template file.</p>

<p>The <code>builders</code> section contains a set of instructions for a particular hypervisor or platform on how to build a VM. For example, it might contain the amount of  RAM, CPU and disk sizes, number and type of interfaces, OS boot instructions and so on.</p>

<p>The <code>provisioners</code> section contains a set of instructions to configure a VM. This section may be as simple as a list of shell scripts or may include a reference to Ansible playbook which will be executed after the VM is built.</p>

<p>You can find my Packer templates along with Ubuntu preseed and provisioner scripts in my <a href="https://github.com/networkop/packer-unl-jenkins">Gihub repository</a>. For those looking for deeper insights about how to build a packer template I can recommend an official Packer <a href="https://www.packer.io/intro/index.html">introduction docs</a>.</p>

<h2>Building a VM with Packer</h2>

<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned previously, I&rsquo;m using Windows as my primary development environment and VMWare Workstation as my hypervisor. Before you begin you also need to have <a href="https://www.packer.io/intro/getting-started/setup.html">Packer</a> and <a href="https://git-scm.com/download/win">git</a> installed.</p>

<pre><code class="winbatch 1. Clone git repository">git clone https://github.com/networkop/packer-unl-jenkins
cd packer-unl-jenkins
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="winbatch 2. Start the build">packer build vmware.json
</code></pre>

<p>With a bit of luck, approximately 30 minutes later you should have a fully configured VM inside your VMWare Workstation waiting to be powered on. These are some of the features of this new VM:</p>

<ul>
<li>4 GB of RAM, 20GB of disk space, 2 dual-core vCPUs</li>
<li>1 Host-only and 1 NAT ethernet interfaces both using DHCP</li>
<li>Jenkins and UNetLab installed</li>
<li>Git and Python PIP packages installed</li>
<li>Username/password are <code>unl/admin</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Once powered on, you should be able to navigate to UNetLab&rsquo;s home page at <code>http://vm_ip:80</code> and Jenkins' home page and <code>http://vm_ip:8080</code>, where <code>vm_ip</code> is the IP of your new VM.</p>

<h2>IOU images</h2>

<p>Unfortunately IOU images are not publicly available so you&rsquo;re gonna have to find them yourself, which shouldn&rsquo;t be too hard. You&rsquo;ll also need to generate a license file for these images which, again, I&rsquo;m not going to discuss in this blog, but I can guarantee that you won&rsquo;t have to look farther than the 1st page of Google search to find all your answers. These are the remaining steps that you need to do:</p>

<ol>
<li>Obtain L2 and L3 IOU images</li>
<li>Generate a license file</li>
<li>Follow <a href="http://www.unetlab.com/2014/11/adding-cisco-iouiol-images/">these instructions</a> to install those images on the UNetLab server</li>
</ol>


<h2>non-DevOps way</h2>

<p>In case you&rsquo;re struggling with Packer here are the list of steps to setup a similar VM manually:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/download/server">Download</a> your favourite Ubuntu Server image. Recommended release at the time of writing is 14.04.4.</li>
<li>Create a VM with at least 4GB of RAM, VT-x support and boot it off the Ubuntu ISO image.</li>
<li>Following instructions <a href="http://www.unetlab.com/2015/08/installing-unetlab-on-a-physical-server/">install Ubuntu and UNetLab</a>.</li>
<li>Install Jenkins as described on <a href="https://wiki.jenkins-ci.org/display/JENKINS/Installing+Jenkins+on+Ubuntu">their wiki website</a></li>
<li>Install additional packages like git and pip. Refer to my Packer <a href="https://github.com/networkop/packer-unl-jenkins/blob/master/scripts/packages.sh">packages script</a> for commands.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Coming up</h2>

<p>In the next post I&rsquo;ll show how to setup Jenkins to do automatic network testing and verification.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Network Continuous Integration and Delivery]]></title>
    <link href="http://networkop.github.io/blog/2016/02/19/network-ci-intro/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://networkop.github.io/blog/2016/02/19/network-ci-intro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this series of posts I&rsquo;ll introduce the tools I&rsquo;ve been using for continuous network development and how they can be used with automation servers like Jenkins for network continuous integration and delivery.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>CI/CD vs ITIL</h2>

<p>How do you implement changes in your network? In today&rsquo;s world there&rsquo;s 95% chance that you have to write up an <abbr title=" Request For Change">RFC</abbr>, submit it at least a week before the planned implementation date, go through at least one <abbr title=" Change Admission Board">CAB</abbr> meeting and only then, assuming it got approved, can you implement it. But the most important question is &lsquo;how do you test&rsquo;? Do you simply content yourself with a few pings or do you make sure all main routes are in place? And how often do you get a call the next morning from a very nervous client asking you to &lsquo;please have a look at the network performance issues&rsquo;?</p>

<p>Software developers have solved most of these problems for themselves. DevOps movement has brought forth ideas of Continuous Integration and Delivery (CI/CD) to streamline the change process and &lsquo;embrace&rsquo; the change rather than protect against it. But how applicable are those ideas to the networks of today? Can we simply rip and replace our CAB meetings with a Jenkins server and live happily ever after?  As always, things are getting difficult as you move down from Layer 7.</p>

<h2>Problem #1 - How to test</h2>

<p>Ever since the dawn of networking, the only tools that engineers could use for testing were traceroutes and pings. It&rsquo;s not necessarily bad since, after all, networks are supposed to be a simple packet transports and shouldn&rsquo;t be endowed with application-layer knowledge. Note that I&rsquo;m talking about traditional or, in SDN-era terms, &lsquo;underlay&rsquo; networks. The biggest problem with network testability is not the lack of test tools but rather lack of automation. For every ping and every traceroute we had to login a device, carefully craft the command including source interface names, VRFs and other various options and then interpret the output.<br/>
I have already explored the idea of automated network testing in my previous blog posts - <a href="http://networkop.github.io/blog/2015/06/15/simple-tdd-framework/">Building Network TDD framework</a> and <a href="http://networkop.github.io/blog/2015/07/17/tdd-quickstart/">Network TDD quickstart</a>. I even got lucky enough to get invited to one of the <a href="http://blog.ipspace.net/2015/11/test-driven-network-development-with.html">greatest networking podcasts</a> hosted by Ivan Pepelnjak.</p>

<h2>Problem #2 - Where to test</h2>

<p>Another big problem is the lack of testable network software. We&rsquo;ve only had IOU, vSRX and vEOS for the past 3-4 years and even now a lot of the real-world functionality remains unvirtualizable. However having those images is a lot better than not, even though some of them tend to crash and behave unreliably from time to time.</p>

<h2>Network CI</h2>

<p>Here I&rsquo;ve come to the actual gist of my post. I want to demonstrate the tools that I&rsquo;ve built and how I use them to automate a lot of the repetitive tasks to prepare for network deployments and upgrades. This is what these tools can do:</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a replica of almost any real-world network topology inside a network emulation environment</li>
<li>Apply configuration to all built devices</li>
<li>Verify real-time connectivity between nodes</li>
<li>Verify traffic flows under various failure conditions against pre-defined set rules</li>
<li>Shutdown and delete the network topology</li>
</ul>


<p>All these steps can be done automatically without making a single click in a GUI or entering a single command in a CLI. This is a sneak peak of what to expect later in the series:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/jiZs0969RWI" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<p>Please don&rsquo;t judge me too harshly, this is my first experience with screencasts.</p>

<h2>Coming up</h2>

<p>In the following posts I&rsquo;ll show how to setup a continuous delivery environment with Jenkins and UNetLab, create test cases and work with configuration files in git version control system to enable automatic testing by Jenkins server. If that sounds interesting to you - stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
