<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>k8s on networkop</title>
    <link>https://networkop.co.uk/tags/k8s/</link>
    <description>Recent content in k8s on networkop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Michael Kashin 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://networkop.co.uk/tags/k8s/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-hosted external DNS resolver for Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-08-k8s-gateway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-08-k8s-gateway/</guid>
      <description>There comes a time in the life of every Kubernetes cluster when internal resources (pods, deployments) need to be exposed to the outside world. Doing so from a pure IP connectivity perspective is relatively easy as most of the constructs come baked-in (e.g. NodePort-type Services) or can be enabled with an off-the-shelf add-on (e.g. Ingress and LoadBalancer controllers). In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll focus on one crucial piece of network connectivity which glues together the dynamically-allocated external IP with a static customer-defined hostname — a DNS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anatomy of the &#34;kubernetes.default&#34;</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-06-kubernetes-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-06-kubernetes-default/</guid>
      <description>Every Kubernetes cluster is provisioned with a special service that provides a way for internal applications to talk to the API server. However, unlike the rest of the components that get spun up by default, you won&amp;rsquo;t find the definition of this service in any of the static manifests and this is just one of the many things that make this service unique.
The Special One To make sure we&amp;rsquo;re on the same page, I&amp;rsquo;m talking about this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving the Ingress Mystery Puzzle</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-06-ingress-puzzle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-06-ingress-puzzle/</guid>
      <description>Last week I posted a tweet about a Kubernetes networking puzzle. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll go over the details of this puzzle and uncover the true cause and motive of the misbehaving ingress.
Puzzle recap Imagine you have a Kubernetes cluster with three namespaces, each with its own namespace-scoped ingress controller. You&amp;rsquo;ve created an ingress in each namespace that exposes a simple web application. You&amp;rsquo;ve checked one of them, made sure it works and moved on to other things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Cluster API using Docker</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-05-cluster-api-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-05-cluster-api-intro/</guid>
      <description>Cluster API (CAPI) is a relatively new project aimed at deploying Kubernetes clusters using a declarative API (think YAML). The official documentation (a.k.a. the Cluster API book), does a very good job explaining the main concepts and goals of the project. I always find that one of the best ways to explore new technology is to see how it works locally, on my laptop, and Cluster API has a special &amp;ldquo;Docker&amp;rdquo; infrastructure provider (CAPD) specifically for that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Simulations with Network Service Mesh</title>
      <link>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-01-nsm-topo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://networkop.co.uk/post/2020-01-nsm-topo/</guid>
      <description>In September 2019 I had the honour to present at Open Networking Summit in Antwerp. My talk was about meshnet CNI plugin, k8s-topo orchestrator and how to use them for large-scale network simulations in Kubernetes. During the same conference, I attended a talk about Network Service Mesh and its new kernel-based forwarding dataplane which had a lot of similarities with the work that I&amp;rsquo;ve done for meshnet. Having had a chat with the presenters, we&amp;rsquo;ve decided that it would be interesting to try and implement a meshnet-like functionality with NSM.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>